A Guide to the Miscellaneous Letters and Documents Collection, 1824-2010
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
- Letter from George E. Bokinsky to All Department Heads and House Staff, 1947, October 31, 1 TLS (mimeograph) (Box-folder 02-040)
  Bokinsky, the Assistant Administrator for the UVa Hospital, informs the staff that the hospital is $300,000 in the red. He states that patients without satisfactory financial arrangements should not be referred for admission unless it is a life-or-death situation. Patients of questionable status are to be referred to the Social Service Department. Letter was found in a notebook belonging to Armistead Page Booker.
- "A Brief Autobiography for My Family" by Charles Shepherd Webb, 1932, 1 pamphlet (Box-folder 02-041)
  Webb writes about his family, studies, work, and principal diseases that came under his care: pneumonia, obstetrics, typhoid fever, diphtheria, influenza, hook worm, and gallstones. Donated by Ann W. McDowell, March 2010.
- Charles Shepherd Webb, n.d., 1 photo 4.5" x 5.25" copy (Box-folder 02-042)
  Donated by Ann W. McDowell, March 2010.
- Charles Shepherd Webb: obituaries, November 28-29, 19--, 2 newspaper clippings, copied (Box-folder 02-043)
- Correlation of the Physical and Vital Forces, n.d., 1 AD fragment, copied (Box-folder 02-044)
- Reprints by Charles Shepherd Webb, 1895-1930, 12 reprints (Box-folder 02-045)
  "Mind and Body" reprinted from Virginia Medical Monthly, June 1895; "Infantile Diarrhea" reprinted from Mobile Medical and Surgical Journal, November 1905; "The Medical Treatment of Gall Stones" read before the Medical Society of Virginia, October 9-12, 1906; "Diphtheria" reprinted from the Old Dominion Journal of Medicine and Sugery, April 1910; "Pneumonia" reprinted from the Medical Record, May 27, 1911; "The Medical Profession and the Public" reprinted from The Charlotte Medical Journal, December 1914; "Puerperal Eclampsia" reprinted from Virginia Medical Monthly, April 1927; "Typhoid Fever" reprinted from Medical Review of Reviews, December 1927; "Some Cases" reprinted from Virginia Medical Monthly, January 1930; "My First Lesson in Anatomy" first published in the Religious Herald, Richmond, Va; "Jeffersonian Democracy, What Is It?" published in the Caroline Progress; "Organotherapy in Pelvic Imbalance" reprinted from The American Physician. Donated by Ann W. McDowell, March 2010.
- University of Virginia Closing Exercises and letter from Mrs. John N. Boland, Exercises: 1900, 1901, 1902, 1903, 1904, 1905; letter: n.d., 5 Closing Exercises booklets bound together (1901-1905) and one which has come loose from the binding (1900) and 1ALS (Box-folder 03-001)
  Two of the University of Virginia Closing Exercises booklets have Micajah Boland's name written on them. Another has M. Boland written on it. Boland was a 1905 graduate of the UVa SOM. Boland (December 1876 or 1877 - May 1968) was a Captain in the U.S. Naval Medical Corps where he served from 1907 to 1937 and then returned in 1939 until 1945. The letter is from his daughter-in-law, Amanda Boland who donated the booklets to the UVa Medical Alumni Association. the Association gave them to HC&S in 2010.
- Letter fragments, November 28, 184[2?], 3 letter fragments (Box-folder 03-002)
  The letter was written from the University of Virginia. Much of the letter is missing, but the writer indicates that he is doing very well in his classes. Some phrases discernable are: breakfast by candlelight, always before sunrise, I find Medicine much more entertaining, professors, Daughters, go to the Episcopalian church, Ladies are few, chapters in the Bible. The UVa Medical Alumni Association gave the fragments to HC&S in 2010.
- Address to Medical Alumni on Alumni Day by Wilhelm Moll, May 7, 1976, 1 TD (Box-folder 03-003)
  Moll thanks the alumni for their support for the new library building that opened the previous month.
- Medical Book, ca. 1870s, 1 AMs with news clippings (Box-folder 03-004)
  The notebook contains a collection of remedies or cures (snake bite, rheumatism, neuralgia, diphtheria, facial paralysis); directions (how to take ink out of linen); and exercises, written in French and English. Pasted on top of these handwritten entries are clippings for cures (croup, cough, nail in the foot, toothache, consumption, burns, headaches, warts, baldness, etc.); directions (how to get rid of rats, crullers, renovate black silk, oyster soup, etc.); and animal care. One of the article clippings advertises the Prairie Farmer Annual for 1871 and includes an article about the Sprague Mower introduced in 1870. Donated by Kae Brown in 2010.
- Physical Therapy and No Smoking, 1977, 1 TD (Box-folder 03-005)
  The document is from the Admissions Department and advises patients to bring equipment from home if it will help them function independently. It also states that as of February 2, 1977, no form of cigarettes or tobacco will be for sale at the Medical Center. Patients are allowed to smoke only in their rooms. Visitors are not allowed to smoke.
- Iron Lung Exhibit guest book 2005-2006, 1 notebook (Box-folder 03-006)
  The notebook was part of the Iron Lung Exhibit which was displayed in the Health Sciences Library. It provided a way for people to comment about the exhibit or share their personal stories.
- Operations by C.Bruce Morton II, MD while at the Mayo Clinic 1925 March 30 - 1927 September 24, 1 notebook (Box-folder 03-007)
  The notebook is in two main sections. The first is called Experimental - Personal and has 6 parts, is handwritten, and contains 770 entries from March 30, 1925 to October 20, 1926. It lists operations and results. The second section is called Clinical - Assistant and consists of carbon copies, has 122 entries, and goes from July 3, 1927 to September 24, 1927. It includes where the patient came from, referring physician if there was one, the personnel involved in the patient's care, a diagnosis, treatment, and summary of the surgery.
- John R. Bookwalter, Interview with Justin Barr and State of Vermont Board of Medical Practice Proposed Decision and Order 2013 August 22, 2011 October 10, 2 TD (Box-folder 03-008)
  Bookwalter is the inventor of the Bookwalter retractor. Justin Barr interviewed Bookwalter because he is writing an article on the history of this surgical instrument. The Vermont Board of Medical Practice determined that Dr. Bookwalter engaged in unprofessional conduct and placed certain limits on his practice.
- Caricatures of University of Virginia faculty members by J. N. Pope '66 1966?, 1 folder with caricatures, copy (Box-folder 03-009)
  James Norfold Pope was a 1966 grraduate of the UVa School of Medicine. His caricatures are compiled in a folder which has the inscription "To Dr. Guerrant with kindest regards and no rhinitis J N Pope '66." In order, the caricatures are David C. Smith; Oliver Beirne Bobbitt Jr.; John M. Nokes ???; Eugene A. Foster; Martin G. Netsky; Chalmers Laughlin Gemmill; Molly: unknown woman; Gene and Molly: unknown; Calvin M. Kunin; George: unknown; Gerald Goldstein; Wild Bill: unknown; Andrew D. Hart; Elton Meredith Alrich; C. Bruce Morton; James Edwin Wood Jr.; James C. Respess; Audrey K. Brown; Frederic B. Westervelt Jr.; Gilbert Simon; Kenneth R. Crispell; James Q. Miller; Julian R. Beckwith; John A. Owen Jr.; Edmund P. Cawley; John L. Guerrant; G. Slaughter Fitz-Hugh; William R. Sandusky; E. Cato Drash and George Minor; William H. Muller Jr.; Charles J. Frankel; Byrd S. Leavell, William B. Hunt Jr., Daniel N. Mohler, and Carlos R. Ayers; Harry, an unprepared lecture: unknown: William Parson; Fritz E. Dreifuss; Lester F. Stewart; Richard W. Garnett Jr.; Jack D. Hain; L. Gordon Kirschner Jr.; Thomas H. Hunter; Joseph Wolpe; Jerrold E. Hammond.
- Case records of C B Morton 1927-1929, 1 folder with three notebooks (Box-folder 03-010)
  Includes typed abstracts of surgical cases from St. Mary's Hospital [Rochester, MN] from June 8, 1927 - August 15, 1927; Typed records of surgical cases from the University of Virginia from December 16, 1927- March 27, 1929; Handwritten 50 Case Records from the University of Virginia from December 16, 1927 - March 27, 1929.
- Diary of Bothwell Graham1934, 1 diary (Box-folder 03-011)
  Bothwell Graham III was a 1937 graduation of the UVa School of Medicine. His diary includes social engagements, what he was doing related to school, and some financial notations.
- "Students' Nursing Practice Record" - Marian Hosfeld1940 September 1, 1 notebook with AN (Box-folder 03-012)
  The Record is from the Hospital of the University of Pennsylvania and is signed by the Superintendent of Nurses, Lucy Masten. It lists over 150 duties, procedures, or treatments that Hosfeld was taught. Each item had a signature by her various supervisors. Several accompanying items are in the artifact collection: a nursing pin 15/16" in diameter, gold in color with red, white and blue paint, marked S of N Universitatis Pennsylvaniensis 1740 on the obverse, and engraved Marian Hosfeld Crosby R.N. on the reverse; three bobby pins; a circle pin 1 1/2"in diameter; and a 3 1/2" long straight hat pin.